
The setup XML specification has the following format:

-----
<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<install>
  one or more install options
</install>
----
An example product specification file is at the bottom of this document.


The INSTALL element:

The install element contains one or more OPTION elements specifying
different install options.

All attribute names are case-sensitive, and are lower-case.
 
There are several required attributes of the install element:

 product    This is used as the product name and as the default top-level
            install directory name.

 desc       This is used a product description string, and is used in
            strings naming the product (title bar, icon description, etc.)

 version    This is the product version string

There are several optional attributes of the install element:

 path       This contains the default directory which will contain the
            product installation directory.  The installation directory
            may be changed by the user at installation time.
            The default is: /usr/local/games

 preinstall This is a shell script which is executed before any options
            are installed.  It is run with the installation destination
            as a command line argument.

 postinstall
            This is a shell script which is executed after all options
            are installed.  It is run with the installation destination
            as a command line argument.

            Both the preinstall and postinstall scripts are run with
            some default environment variables set. Look at the 'SCRIPT'
            section below for a detailed list.

 eula       This is a file which contains a text license agreement that
            must be agreed to by the user before the installation will
            proceed.

 readme     This is the README file for the product, the user will be
            prompted to see it before the installation begins. The default
            value is "README" if not specified and such a file is
            actually present.

 url        This is a web site which is launched after the install is
            completed.

 localurl   This is the local HTML file that is loaded if the network
            is down, or the web site cannot be reached.  It should be
            specified as a path relative to the setup working directory.
            This is a secondary URL, and should not be specified without
            also specifying a primary URL in the "url" attribute.

 auto_url   This is a flag which tells whether or not to automatically
            launch the web browser on the product URL.  It can be either
            "true" to launch the browser, or "false" to prompt the user.
            The default behavior is to prompt the user as to whether or
            not to launch the web browser.

 cdrom      If this attribute has the value "required", then the installer
            will abort if no CDROM is currently mounted on the system.


The OPTION element:

The option element contains text describing the element, along with
zero or more option, binary, files, and script elements.

There is currently no way to specify relationships of options at the
same level;  each may be installed independently of any other.  If
an option is dependent upon another option, it must be inside the
body of that option:

    <option>
        Top-level option
        <option>
            First dependent option
        </option>
        <option>
            Second dependent option
        </option>
    </option>

Nested options will not be available unless the top-level option is
selected.

There are several optional attributes of the option element:

 install    If this attribute is set to "true", then the option will
            be installed by default.  It may be deselected by the user.

 help       This attribute is a help string which is displayed to the
            user if the user requests more information about the option.

 arch       This option is only available on the specified architecture.
            The architecture can be one of:
               x86, ppc, alpha, sparc64, etc.

 libc       This option is only available with the specified version of libC.
            The version can be one of:
               libc5, glibc-2.0, glibc-2.1, etc.


The BINARY element:

The binary element contains a single binary file to be installed for
this option.  The binary is installed in the top level of the install
directory, and if the symlink attribute is set, a symbolic link is
placed in the system executable path.

The actual file that is copied resides in bin/<arch>/<libc>/, where
"<arch>" is the current architecture string (x86, ppc, alpha, etc.)
and "<libc>" is an optional C library version (glibc-2.0, glibc-2.1, etc.)

For example, if you wanted to install an executable file named "foo"
on a PPC system, you would need it on the install disk as bin/ppc/foo.
If it depended upon version 2.1 of the GNU C library, you would place
it on the install disk as bin/ppc/glibc-2.1/foo.

There are several required attributes of the binary element:

 arch       "any" is synonymous with the current architecture. You can also
            use this attribute to force a precise architecture, for example
            "ppc" or "sparc64".

 libc       "any" is synonymous with the current libc version. This can
            also be used to force a libc version for the binary, i.e
            "glibc-2.0" or "glibc-2.1".

There are several optional attributes of the binary element:

 symlink    This is a symbolic link that is installed in the system path
            and points to the installed binary.

 icon       This is an optional icon file that you should install into
            the top level of the install directory.  If both a symlink
            and an icon are specified for a binary, it will also have a
            desktop icon or menu item created for it, if the user wishes.

 menu       This is an optional submenu that the application menuitem is
            installed into.  If no submenu is defined, the menu item will
            be placed in the "Games" submenu.

 name       This is an optional name for the menu entry.  By default the
            name of the product is used. 

 cdrom      If this attribute has a "yes" value, then setup will look for
            the file on one of the mounted CDROMs on the system.

The FILES element:

The files element contains a list of files and directories, one per line,
which are installed for this option.

You may specify relative paths and shell wildcard patterns for the files.

There are several optional attributes of the files element:

 path       This is a system path that these files should be installed into.

 cdrom      If this attribute has a "yes" value, then setup will look for
            the files on one of the mounted CDROMs on the system.


The SCRIPT element:

The script element contains shell commands which are executed when the
option is installed.  You may interleave multiple script and files
elements, and they will be installed/executed in the order in which
they appear.

If you call a script on the installation medium, remember that the
medium may be mounted without executable permissions, so the script
file should be called using the name of the script interpreter.

For example:

    <script>
        sh setup.data/stage1.sh
    </script>

There are no attributes for the script element.

The following environment variables are defined while in the shell script:
    SETUP_PRODUCTNAME   : Product name from the XML file
    SETUP_PRODUCTVER    : Product version from the XML file
    SETUP_INSTALLPATH   : Installation path of the data files
    SETUP_SYMLINKSPATH  : Path where symbolic links for the binary files
                          will be placed.

-------------------------------------------------------------------------

Example XML product specification:
(Note:  There can be no comments within the file itself, so we will denote
        comments using '# ..." notation)

<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<install product="foo" desc="An example product" version="1.0"
         path="/opt"
         preinstall="sh setup.data/foo-preinst.sh $*"
         postinstall="sh setup.data/foo-postinst.sh $*"
         eula="license.txt"
         url="http://www.products.kom/foo/index.html"
>
  # This installs a product named "foo" in /opt/foo by default.
  # The user may specify a different installation directory.
  # The installer will prompt the user with the license contained in the
  # file "license.txt", and will execute foo-preinst.sh and foo-postinst.sh
  # before and after installing the product.  When the product is finished
  # installing, a browser will be launched to the site:
  #     http://www.products.kom/foo/index.html

    <option install="true" help="Required for use">
        Base Install  # Option called "Base Install" contains a binary,
                      # some data files, and two optional editors.
        <binary arch="any" libc="any" symlink="foo" icon="icon.xpm">
            foo
        </binary>
        <files>
            README
            icon.xpm
            edit.xpm
            data/*.dat
        </files>
        <option help="terminal editor for foo data files">
            Curses Editor
            <binary arch="any" libc="any">
                foo-edit.ncurses
            </binary>
        </option>
        <option help="X windows editor for foo data files">
            Motif Editor
            <binary arch="any" libc="any">
                foo-edit.motif
            </binary>
        </option>
        <script>
            # A script to finish the editor installation
            # It would set the default editor and edit desktop menu items
            # The first parameter to the script is the install path
            sh setup.data/edit-postinst.sh $*
        </script>
    </option>
    <option>
        Extra Data  # Option called "Extra Data" contains extra files
        <files>
            extra/*.dat
        </files>
    </option>
</install>

-------------------------------------------------------------------------
